American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IId. 1837-1844 APS.Archives.IId APS.Archives.IId
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Nov. 7, 1842; 9-3/4x8; Royal Society of Arts (Great Britain)
    L.S.: W.A.Graham. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings and Transactions
  - Letter to George Ord, November 7, 1842; 7 1/2" x 9 3/16"; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850
    Treasurer of the A.P.S., London, 2 pp., address and endorsement. L.S. Understands that some trunks of Dr. [Benjamin] Franklin's papers have been recovered, containing letters of members of the Vaughan family. Requests copies. FILM54-61 FRAME141
  - Letter to G[eorge] Ord, November 11, 1842; 8" x 9 7/8"; Tidyman, Philip
    Charleston, S. C., 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Acknowledges receipt of letter from Mr. Ord. "I am glad to know you have found the Autographs."
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Nov. 14, 1842; 9x7-1/4; Cambridge Philosophical Society
  - Letter to J[ohn] Vaughan, Philadelphia, Nov. 18, 1842; 10x8; Society of Antiquaries of London
  - Letter to George Ord, November 28, 1842; Humphreys, Samuel, 1778-1846
  - Mrs. [Samuel George] Morton to [George] Ord, December 2, 1842; 5" x 7 7/8"; Morton, Samuel George, Mrs.
    [Philadelphia], 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Regrets that Dr. Morton will be unable to lecture before the A.P.S. due to illness.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Dec. 5, 1842; 10x8; Akademie der Wissenschaften in Göttingen
    Göttingen, A.L.S.: J.Fr.L. Hausmann. 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for Proceedings and Transactions
  - Letter to Geo[rge] Ord, Philadelphia, Dec. 9, 1842; 10x8; Burnham, George
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.,end.by J.K.Kane, and add., end. Asks payment for bill due M. W. Baldwin.
  - Receipt to the American philosophical society for work on the Franklin portrait, per order of Dr. Chapman, Dec. 9, 1842; 4-1/2x6-1/2; Scarlett, Samuel
    Philadelphia, D. 1p.and end. FILM54-66 FRAME118
  - Letter to George Ord, December 9, 1842; 4 1/2" x 7 1/8"; Sully, Thomas, 1783-1872
    ----, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Received from Mr. [John] Vaughan in June, 1840, $200 for portrait of Mr. [Joel R.] poinsett.
  - Letter to R[obert] M. Patterson, December 14, 1842; 7 7/8" x 9 3/4"; Olmsted, Edward
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsements. A.L.S. Demand that A.P.S. return $2,500 observatory fund to city; otherwise suit for recovery will be instituted.
  - Letter to Sears C. Walker, December 15, 1842; 8" x 9 3/4"; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsements. A.L.S. Forwards letter from [Edward] Olmsted, in re claim of city for $2,500 against the A.P.S.
  - Report of committee on trust funds, Dec. 16, 1842; 9-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia] D. 1p. and end.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Dec. 19, 1842; 10x8; Natural History Society of Northumberland, Durham, & Newcastle-upon-Tyne
    Newcastle, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Wm.Hutton and Edward Charlton. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to Robley Dunglison, December 19, 1842; 8 7/8" x 11"; Ridgway, George William
    Secretary of the A.P.S., Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. A.P.S. put upon the distribution list of the Literary Age.
  - Letter to George Ord, December 20, 1842; 7" x 8 3/4"; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845
    Paris, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Approves appointment of M. Bossange as agent of the Society. Has distributed memoir of Professor Bache to persons to whom it was directed.
  - Letter to George Ord, December 20, 1842; 7" x 8 7/8"; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845
    Paris, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Duplicate. Approves appointment of M. Bossange as agent of the Society. Has distributed memoir of Professor Bache to persons to whom it was directed.
  - Report of committee on Isaac Lea's paper:, Dec. 22, 1842; 6-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    "Description of new freshwater shells"; Philadelphia, D.S.: Isaac Hays, S. G. Morton, and T. R. Peale. 1p._4 end.
  - Receipt to the American philosophical society for framing the Franklin portrait, Dec. 26, 1842; 4x7-1/2; Earle, James
    D.S. 1p.and end. This was ordered by Dr. Chapman.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Dec., 1842; 9-3/4x8; Zoological Society of London
  - Letter to A[lexander] D[allas] Bache, 1842; 4 7/8" x 7 7/8"; Peale, Franklin, 1795-1870
    ----, ----, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Declines invitation to furnish a paper for the centennial celebration of the American Philosophical Society.
  - Letter to George Ord, January 2, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    Washington, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Does not think he has been paid twice for work on a index for the A.P.S.
  - Letter to Edward Olmsted, January 2, 1843; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Walker, Sears Cook, 1805-1853
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Copy. The chairman of the committee on trust funds inquires of the city solicitor as to the acceptability of a bond for $2,500, payable in ten years, with interest half yearly at 6 per cent per annum.
  - Letter to George Ord, January 3, 1843; 7 1/2" x 9 1/4"; Vaughan, Petty, 1788-1854
    London, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Scientific memoirs subscribed to by the A.P.S. Is sending parcel in a box to Mr. [John] Penington, on packet the 8th. inst.
  - Letter to Geo[rge] Ord, January 5, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Cresson, Elliott, 1796-1854
    Secretary of the A.P.S., Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Presents to the A.P.S.: a work by his friend, Luke Howard.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Jan. 5, 1843; 15x9; Geological Society of London
    Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Wm. J. Hamilton. 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to S[ears] C. Walker, January 5, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 3/4"; Olmsted, Edward
    Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. The city solicitor is instructed to accept terms offered by A.P.S. in letter of January 2, for settlement of debt due by A.P.S. to city of Philadelphia.
  - Letter to the Secretary of the A.P.S., January 6, 1843; 5" x 7"; Walker, Charles J.
    [London], 1 p. and endorsement. A.N.S. The London Electrical Society forwards its Proceedings to the A.P.S.
  - Letter to George Ord, January 7, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    L-8 Washington, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Concerning mistake in accounts of the publication committee of the A.P.S.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Jan. 10, 1843; 10x8; Lyceum of Natural History (New York, N. Y.)
    New York, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: John H. Redfield. 1p.,end.: A.D.B[ache] and add. Thanks for Transactions.
  - Receipt to [David Bailie] Warden for payment for the American philosophical society, Jan. 11, 1843; 5x8; Bossange, Hector, 1795-1884
    Paris, D.S.: A. Morely. 1p.,end.: "pour monsr. Ord", and end. In French.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Jan. 13, 1843; 10x8; Harvard University
    Cambridge, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Josiah Quincy, Pres.and Thaddeus William Harris, Librarian. 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for Transactions and Proceedings.
  - Account for preparing index for the first four volumes of the American philosophical society's Transactions, Jan. 18, 1843; 10x7-1/2; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    Philadelphia, A.D.S. 1p.,end.and end.by Jno.Penington.
  - Report of committee appointed for the purpose of having portrait of Benjamin Franklin cleaned and repaired, Jan. 20, 1843; 9-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia] D.S.: N. Chapman, G. Ord, and Geo. W. Smith. 1p.; end. FILM 54-62 FRAME93
  - Letter to G[eorge] Ord, January 20, 1843; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Bossange, Edouard
    Librarian of A.P.S., New York, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Returns bill of lading for proper endorsement.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Jan. 24, 1843; 10x8; Royal Society of Arts (Great Britain)
    L.S.: Francis Whishaw. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to G[eorge] Ord, January 25, 1843; 4 15/16" x 7 15/16"; Peale, Franklin, 1795-1870
    ----, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Wishes to borrow the Society's copy of Bishop [William] White's address upon Girard College.
  - Statement of accounts to the American philosophical society for case of fossils from Lesueur, Jan. 26, 1843; 4-1/2x8; Bossange, Edouard
    New York, A.D.S. 1p.and add.: [George O]rd, end.
  - Letter to G[eorge] Ord, January 26, 1843; 8 1/4" x 10 3/4"; Bossange, Edouard
    New York, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Acknowledges receipt of letter of [January] 21st. Has obtained two boxes from the custom house, and has forwarded them to Mr. Ord.
  - Letter to G[eorge] Ord, February 3, 1843; 8 1/4" x 10 3/4"; Bossange, Edouard
    New York, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Acknowledges receipt of letter of [January] 28th., together with a box for Paris, "which has been attended to."
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Feb. 3, 1843; 10x7-1/2; Linnean Society of London
  - Letter to Geo[rge] Ord, February 6, 1843; 5" x 8"; Fraley, F. (Frederick), 1804-1901
    Walnut St., [Philadelphia], 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Requests Mr. Ord's attendance at meeting of committee on Mr. [Joseph] Parker's mortgage.
  - Letter to George Ord, February 7, 1843; 4 15/16" x 7 7/8"; Robertson, J.
    ----, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Returns five volumes of Hansard's Parliamentary debates to the A.P.S.
  - Report of committee on the mortgage as affecting the museum property, Feb. 10, 1843; 10x8; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia] D.S.: F. Fraley, Sam. Breck, Hartman Kuhn, and Henry J. Williams. 4p. and end. See APS Proc., II, 252-253.
  - Letter to George Ord, Secretary of the A.P.S., February 13, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Mercer, Hugh
    Fredericksburg, Va., 2 pp., address and endorsement. Circumstances attending the donation to the A.P.S. of the autograph correspondence of General [George] Weedon.
  - Letter to George Ord, Librarian of the A.P.S., February 18, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Mercer, Hugh
    Fredericksburg, Va., 1p., address and endorsements. A.L.S. Donates to the A.P.S.: "some very interesting and authentic papers" concerning the public career of his father, General Hugh Mercer. See Pro., II, 254.
  - Letter to R[obley] Dunglison, February 22, 1843; 7 7/8" X 9 7/8"; Gurley, Ralph Randolph, 1797-1872
    Secretary of the A.P.S., Washington, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Offers to send the African Repository to the A.P.S. Library. See Pro., II, 254.
  - Letter to Geo[rge] Ord, February 23, 1843; 4 7/8" x 7 5/8"; Mease, James, 1771-1846
    [Philadelphia], 2 pp., address and endorsement. 3d. per. L. With regard to the return of some books (not named) to the A.P.S. library. Sends first number of L'Institut to complete the volume.
  - Letter to G[eorge] Ord, February 25, 1843; 8 1/4" x 10 3/4"; Bossange, Edouard
    New York, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Acknowledges of letter of the 20th. Box has been shipped to Havre "long ago." Regrets illness of Mr. Penington.
  - Letter to George Ord, February 25, 1843; 8 3/8" x 10 5/8"; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878
    Librarian of A.P.S., Princeton College, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Brought two books to Philadelphia, intending to return them to A.P.S., but they were packed and taken back to Princeton. FILM 235 FRAME 14
  - Letter to S[ears] C. Walker, February 27, 1843; 8" x 10"; Olmsted, Edward
    1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. The city solicitor of Philadelphia inquires whether the A.P.S. will deliver a bond for the amount owing by them to the city.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Feb. 28, 1843; 10x8; Muséum national d'histoire naturelle (France)
    Paris, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Jussieu, Milne-Edwards and E.Chevreul. 1p.,end. In French. Thanks for Transactions and Proceedings
  - Letter to George Ord, February 28, 1843; 5" x 7 7/8"; Snider, Jacob
    Treasurer of the A.P.S., Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Wishes to meet Mr. Ord in order to explain some of John Vaughan's accounts.
  - Letter to the American Philosophical Society, February?, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 13/16"; Cogswell, William, 1787-1850
    [Hanover, N. H., ] --, 2pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. The Northern Academy of Arts and Sciences, through its secretary, solicits a set of the A.P.S. Transactions.
  - Report of committee on Centennial Celebration, March 3, 1843; 10x7-1/2; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia] D.S.: N. Chapman, J. K. Kane, F. Fraley, John Ludlow, and R. Dunglison. 2p. and end. Mentions B. Franklin. See APS Proc., II, 255-256. FILM54-63 FRAME94
  - Letter to George Ord, March 3, 1843; 7 1/2" x 9 1/4"; Vaughan, Petty, 1788-1854
    Treasurer of A.P.S., London, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Will send three numbers of journals requested together with some other parcels and letters of thanks to the A.P.S.
  - Letter to George Ord, March 6, 1843; 7 1/2" x 9 1/4"; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850
    London, 1 p., address and endorsement. L.S. Concerning parcels sent to A.P.S. and A. D. Bache via the Thomas P. Cope.
  - Letter to J[ohn] K. Kane, Philadelphia, March 7, 1843; 9-3/4x7-3/4; New-York Historical Society
    New York, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Frederic De Peyster. 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for Transactions.
  - Letter to the American Philosophical society, March 8, 1843; 9x7-1/2; Asiatic Society of Bengal
    Calcutta, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: H.Pritchington 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for Transactions and Proceedings
  - Letter to [George] Ord, March 14, 1843; 5" x 8"; Grinnan, Robert A.
    Librarian of A.P.S., Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Requests acknowledgment of receipt of package from Col. [Hugh] Mercer of Virginia.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, March 22, 1843; 10x8-1/2; Bataviaasche genootschap von kunsten en wetenschappen
    Amsterdam, L.S.: Vrolik. 1p.,end. In French. Thanks for Transactions and forwards publication.
  - Letter to the American Philosophical Society, March 29, 1843; 7 5/8" x 9 7/8"; Campbell, Quintin, 1774-1863
    Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Inquires whether the Athenaeum can secure a five or six year lease of the rooms now being occupied by them.
  - Letter to G[eorge] Ord, March 30, 1843; 8" x 10 1/4"; Bossange, Hector, 1795-1884
    Librarian of A.P.S., Paris, 2 pp. and endorsement. A.L.S. (In French). Acknowledges receipt of letters of November 13, 1842 and January 20, 1843. Instructions being observed. Book news.
  - Committee on centennial celebration to ----, March 31, 1843; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. Pr.L. Circular letter of invitation to the centennial celebration.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, March, 1843; 10x8; Bowditch Library
    Boston, A.L.S.: H.I.Bowditch. 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for Proceedings and Transactions Have several parcels from London for the APS, Franklin institute, DuPonceau, etc.
  - Letter to P[eter] S. DuPonceau, April 2, 1843; 7 3/8" x 8 15/16"; Longman, Brown and Company
    President of A.P.S., London, 1 p., address and endorsement. L. Advertising "a valuable Scientific Work on Ornithology by Mr. G. Gray of the British Museum."
  - Letter to George Ord, April 3, 1843; 7 3/8" x 9 1/8"; Vaughan, Petty, 1788-1854
    Treasurer of A.P.S., London, 1 p. address and endorsement. A.L.S. Details concerning publications forwarded to the A.P.S.
  - Letter to Alexander Dallas Bache, April 4, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Bartlett, W. H. C. (William Holms Chambers), 1804-1893
    West Point, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Concerning a paper he has prepared for the centennial celebration of A. P. S. Will be unable to attend the meeting in person.
  - Letter to George Ord, April 7, 1843; 8 3/8" x 10 5/8"; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878
    Librarian of A.P.S., Princeton, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Returns two books to the A.P.S. Hopes to be present at meeting of (April) 17. FILM 235 FRAME 15
  - Letter to [the American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia], April 7, 1843; 7 5/8" x 9 5/8"; Mease, James, 1771-1846
    1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. With regard to the terms of presentation, in 1835, of a manuscript orderly book kept at the American camp at Valley Forge, and some autograph letters to General [George] Weedon.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, April 11, 1843; 7 11/16" x 9 3/4"; Lowell, Charles, 1782-1861
    President of A.P.S., Boston, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. The secretary of the Massachusetts Historical Society invites the A.P.S. to join in the second centennial celebration of the confederation of New England.
  - Letter to R[obert] M. Patterson, April 12, 1843; 7 7/8" x 10"; Porter, J. M.
    Washington, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Acknowledges receipt of letter from the A.P.S. thanking him "for appropriating means to continue the Magnetic observations heretofore conducted under the auspices of the society."
  - Letter to the American Philosophical Society, April 12, 1843; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    The estate of John Vaughan deceased.
  - Letter to George Ord, April 13, 1843; 7 15/16" x 9 7/8"; Graham, J. D. (James Duncan), 1799-1865
    Treasurer of A.P.S., Washington, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Directions regarding fifty extra copies of bulletin no. 25 of Proceedings of the A.P.S.
  - Letter to Jacob Snider, jr., Hall of the A.P.S., April 13, 1843; 7 15/16" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    [Philadelphia], 2 pp. A.L.S. Submits statement of sums due to the American Philosophical Society from John Vaughan to the executor of Vaughan's estate for settlement.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, April 17, 1843; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Académie des sciences (France)
    Paris, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: F.Arago. 1p.,end. In French. Thanks for Proceedings and Transactions
  - Letter to the American Philosophical Society, April 18, 1843; 8" x 9"; Rafn, Carl Christian, 1795-1864
    Copenhagen, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Sends to the A.P.S.: some Memoires of the Royal Society of Northern Antiquaries.
  - Letter to N[athaniel] Chapman, April 20, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Gilmor, Robert, 1774-1848
    Baltimore, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Will be pleased to attend the hundredth anniversary of the A.P.S. FILM 403 FRAME 3-2
  - Letter to ----, April 21, 1843; 4 7/8" x 8"; Rümker, Carl, 1788-1862
    Hamburg, 3pp. and endorsement. A.Com.S. Presents table of occultations of fixed stars. Read, July 23, 1843.
  - Letter to Geo[rge] Ord, April 24, 1843; 5" x 7 15/16"; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    Librarian of A.P.S., ----, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Requests loan of Nautical Almanac for 1836.
  - Letter to Robley Dunglison, Philadelphia, April 24, 1843; 10x8; National Institute for the Promotion of the Sciences
    Washington, L.S.: Francis Markoe. 1p.,end. Thanks for Proceedings and Transactions from the APS.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, April 25, 1843; 10x8; Harvard University
    Cambridge, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Josiah Quincy, Pres.and Thaddeus William Harris, Librarian. 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for Proceedings and Transactions.
  - Letter to the American Philosophical society, Philadelphia, April 25, 1843; 10x8; Lyceum of Natural History (New York, N. Y.)
    New-York, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: John H. Redfield. 1p.,end.and add.: "G.Ord's box." Thanks for Transactions.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, April 25, 1843; 10-1/2x8; Société de géographie (France)
    Paris, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: S.Berthelot 1p.,end.and add. In French. Thanks for Transactions.
  - Letter to N[athaniel] Chapman and others, April 26, 1843; 8" x 9 7/8"; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852
    Washington, 1 p. L.S. Hopes to attend hundredth anniversary of the A.P.S.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, April 27, 1843; 10x8; Northern academy of arts and sciences, Hanover, N.H.
    Hanover, N.H., Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: William Cogswell. 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for Proceedings.
  - Letter to George Ord, April 27, 1843; 8 3/4" x 10 3/4"; Snider, Jacob
    jr,. to George Ord, Treasurer of the A.P.S., Philadelphia, 2 pp. A.L.S. Refusal to recognize claims made by Ord against the estate of John Vaughan. See Ord to Snider, April 13, 1843.
  - Letter to George Ord, Philadelphia, April 28, 1843; 10x8; Massachusetts Historical Society
    Boston, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Joseph B. Felb. 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for Transactions.
  - Letter to George Ord, April 28, 1843; 7 3/8" x 9 1/8"; Vaughan, Petty, 1788-1854
    London, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Submits account of £4.1.1, exclusive of Altona volumes. Yarrell's Birds charged to William Vaughan.
  - Account with Geo[rge] Ord, April 28, 1843 - August 16, 1844; 8x10; Vaughan, Petty, 1788-1854
    D.S. 1p.and end. Business for the American philosophical society.
  - Letter to A[lexander] D[allas] Bache, April 29, 1843; 7 7/8" x9 7/8"; Graham, J. D. (James Duncan), 1799-1865
    Washington, 2 pp. A.L.S. Hopes to attend centennial celebration. May present paper embracing his observations in Texas, or on the northeastern boundary.
  - John Quincy Adams to the Committee of the A.P.S., May 1, 1843; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848
    Washington, 1 p. A.L.S. Regrets that an engagement in Boston will prevent him from attending the centennial anniversary of the A.P.S.
  - Receipt to the American philosophical society for taxes paid on ground rent, May 1, 1843; 5-1/2x7-1/2; Graff, Charles
    Philadelphia, D. 1p.,end.by [George Ord],and end.
  - Letter to the Committee of the A.P.S., Worcester, May 1, 1843; 7 15/16" x 9 7/8"; Thomas, Benjamin Franklin, 1813-1878
    1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. The American Antiquarian Society, through its secretary, accepts the invitation to the hundredth anniversary of the A.P.S.
  - Letter to [Robley] Dunglison, Philadelphia, May 1, 1843; 9x7; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p.,end.and add. Thanks for publications from the APS. Refers to Arago. Forwards one of his own publications. Not found May, 2011.
  - Calculation of taxes on the income from the Magellanic fund, May 2, 1843; 5-1/2x3-1/2; American Philosophical Society
    D.in hand of George Ord. 1p.and end.
  - Letter to C[lement] C. Biddle, May 2, 1843; 7 3/4" x 9 7/8"; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    [Philadelphia], 2pp. A.L.S. Will be unable to meet the committee of finance this afternoon. Duty to present a statement of accounts to Mr. Vaughan's executor.
  - Letter to George Ord, May 3, 1843; 7 3/8" x 9 1/4"; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850
    London, 1 p. L.S. Inventory of a parcel sent to the A.P.S. in a packet for the Franklin Institute.
  - Letter to George Ord, May 4, 1843; 4 5/16" x 7"; Condie, D. Francis (David Francis), 1796-1875
    [Philadelphia], 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. The secretary of the College of Physicians requests the use of A.P.S. rooms for a meeting on the evening of May 16.
  - Letter to A. D. Bache, May 4, 1843; 7 7/8" x 10"; Mower, Thomas G., ca. 1790-1852
    New York, 1 p. and address. A.L.S. Will be unable to attend centennial celebration of A.P.S., but hopes to send communication on "meteorological enquiries now in progress at our military posts."
  - Letter to A[lexander] D[allas] Bache and John Ludlow, May 5, 1843; 8" x 9 7/8"; Abert, John James, 1788-1863